Guide to the Semple Street Food Co-op, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, 1972-1985 AIS.1991.20
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Semple Street Food Co-op, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records
1972-1985
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Semple Street Food Co-op (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
AIS.1991.20
1.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
The Semple Street Food Cooperative Association was one of many cooperatively owned and managed natural food stores established in the United States during the 1960s and 1970s. Incorporated in 1972, it set up operations in the Oakland neighborhood of Pittsburgh at 3459 Ward St. (the corner of Ward and Semple). Records of the Semple Street Food Cooperative, Inc. include articles of incorporation, board meeting minutes, bylaws, policies, financial records, member correspondence, and community bulletin board ephemera.
History
The Semple Street Food Cooperative Association was one of many cooperatively owned and managed food stores established in the United States during the 1960s and 1970s. Building on principles established by a consumer-owned store established in Rochdale, England in 1844, these new American cooperatives helped establish the natural foods industry. The Semple Street Co-op was incorporated in 1972 under the District of Columbia Food Cooperative Association Act, and set up operations in Pittsburgh at 3459 Ward St. (corner of Ward and Semple), in an Oakland storefront that had formerly been Reiser's Drug Store. During its 12 years of operation, the Co-op's membership regularly elected a Board of Directors, and dues were paid monthly, either in cash, or volunteer work hours. By assuming part ownership in the business, members were able to order food and household necessities in bulk, and consume them at or near wholesale prices. When the Cooperative disintegrated in 1985, remaining personnel and equipment were transferred to Pittsburgh's East End Food Co-op.
Scope and Content Notes
Records of the Semple Street Food Cooperative, Inc. include articles of incorporation, board meeting minutes, bylaws, policies, financial records, member correspondence, and community bulletin board ephemera. The bulk of the records are financial in nature.
"Policy and Management" contains Board meeting minutes, employee policies and ballots. The "Federation of Ohio River Cooperatives" (FORC) is a wholesale supplier and regional cooperative organizer, based in Columbus, Ohio. The FORC newsletter includes price listings illustrating the types of items that would have been in stock at the co-op. "Community Relations and Donations" documents more proactive relationships that the Cooperative maintained with civic, cultural, and charity organizations in the Pittsburgh region, including evidence of a youth internship program. "Supplier Invoices" include a list of retail magazine subscriptions and community advertising, and legal and accounting fees.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Robert Opie Shepherd in 1991.
Previous Citation
Semple Street Food Co-op, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, 1972-1985, AIS.1991.20, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Records of Cooperatives in Pittsburgh, ais 91:20, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
Records of the East End Food Co-op, Pittsburgh, Pa., 1987-1996, AIS.1997.42, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Separated Material
Some records of this collection relating to the East End Co-op were transferred to Records of the East End Food Co-op, Pittsburgh, PA, 1987-1996, AIS.1997.42.
Food industry and trade -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Associations; Food cooperatives -- Pennsylania -- Pittsburgh; Cooperative societies -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.); East End Food Co-op (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Semple Street Food Co-op (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
- Articles of Incorporation and Bylaws, 1974-82 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Semple Street Cooperative Association Corporate Seal and Stamp, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Policy and Management, 1981 and undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Federation of Ohio River Cooperatives (FORC) Newsletter, Vol. 1, No. 10, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Flyers and Broadsheets, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Community Relations and Donations, 1978-83 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Supplier Invoices, 1984-85 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Sales Charts, 1973-78 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Financial Records, 1972-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9-20)
- Disbursements and receipts, 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 21-25)